Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning
about the chemistry behind electrolytes,
specifically those found within solutions,
which as many of you know, you see
advertisements all over the place in
terms of Gatorade commercials, Powerade,
all these different types of things that
we can ingest for going to the gym about
how you need electrolytes to replenish
your body and to help you move forward.
Well, really, what exactly are they?
Well, when it comes to electrolytes, the
whole idea is that they are different
salts that we have in our body.
So if you think of salts, like table salt,
they have at home, sodium chloride, right?
Where you have sodium and you also
have chlorine ions all bound together.
And one thing about that is, well,
if you ingest salt, well, is it
going to still exist as a crystal?
Well, if you were to throw salt
in water, what happens to it?
So last time you made rice or
pasta at home, did it sit there
and stay in its crystalline form?
And one thing you can imagine is
all the little water molecules.
all around in that glass of water are
going to start surrounding those ions.
They're attracted because waters,
as you can imagine, have a partial
positive, partial negative side.
They're going to be attracted
to all these little ions.
Now, when you get enough of them, they
work together through ion dipole forces.
To break these molecules apart
or break these compounds apart
into their individual ions, so
they'll surround and conquer them.
So when it comes to different ionic
compounds, we're always interested
in trying to figure out exactly
how are they dissociating, meaning,
how are they breaking apart?
One thing turns into two.
So breaking apart, so these electrolytes
is really the thing that's going to be the
focus of this video, especially when we're
looking in solutions and just a little
bit of a reminder, what are they solutions
or anytime you have a homogenous mixture.
So one example of that is.
If you look around you, right, the air
that you can't really see, that is a
homogeneous mixture being that the solvent
is nitrogen and your solute is oxygen.
So the solute is the minor component.
The solvent is the major component.
Another example is if you go
back to salt and water above.
Right.
The salt is the solute
that we had in solution.
And this aqueous tells you, Hey, that
you have water as your solvent and
is dissolving all these ions that are
in solution to help them break apart.
So let's take a look at what these
electrolytes are all about, how we
can label them and learn the different
types of them and how you can identify
them in your chemistry course.
So starting off electrolytes are
substances whose aqueous solution.
is a conductor of electricity,
meaning that these ions, which are
positive, negative attract charge.
So whenever you have charges,
well, you can actually
conduct electricity with them.
This is what your, these different
commercials, when you think of
Gatorades and professional athletes,
all showing how they are being used
all the time to help fuel them.
It's to help make them better, right?
And to function better.
Electrolytes are something that's
essential for your body to function.
There are many different types of them
because what they do is inside of your
actual bloodstream and around your
cells, they cause different chemical
electro and electrostatic gradients
within the cells to help cause different
ions to flow, causing ATP to be
generated, which helps your body move.
And that's very, very important.
So to label them, the first
type, there are three overall.
The first one is strong electrolytes.
So when you think of strong, think
of really, really, really muscular.
The way that we label these is
that these are all ionic compounds.
Meaning that they will dissolve
and they will dissociate into ions.
So what we, the way we label
ionic compounds is all of them are
referred to as strong electrolytes.
And that's because ionic
compounds will dissolve in
water due to ion dipole forces.
So whenever we are labeling these,
the way to remember is all ionic,
strong acids, strong bases, are all
considered to be strong electrolytes.
Because they all can be
broken apart by water.
And you might be like, wait a minute, Dr.
Dan, what about solubility rules?
Aren't some of them
considered to be insoluble?
And that's true, some
of them are insoluble.
But, even though they are labeled
as insoluble, the very, very, very,
very tiny percentage of them do
break apart into ions, and they're
still labeled as strong electrolytes.
We might not show them in a chemical
equation, but you still could
label it as a strong electrolyte.
So these are a little bit easier than
having to work with solubility tables
and all those other different methods.
Let's look at the next type.
Weak electrolytes.
So weak electrolytes are whenever a very
small percentage of the molecules in
water, they are dissolved by the solvent.
However, they don't all dissociate.
They don't all break
apart into their ions.
In fact, a very small
percentage of them do.
So all of them are soluble, they're
all polar, but some of them will,
most of them will stay as their actual
molecular form or as covalent molecules.
So when these exist, you'll have
very few ions, we're talking like 0.
1 to 5 percent of them
will actually dissociate.
Now a way that we can label weak
electrolytes for easy context, for this
course, and for introductory chemistry.
is that all the weak acids and weak bases
are considered to be weak electrolytes.
So, how do you exactly know when it's
a weak, a weak acid versus a weak base?
Well, for you guys, there is a
list of strong acids and bases that
you can find on the green sheet.
And if you're someone that's watching
this video that's not in my course,
then there's a video on this sheet.
It's called the green sheet.
It's our solubility video.
Take a look at it so
you can find out more.
So if you are actually looking at
looking at this thing, there is a
list of strong acids and strong bases.
Find it for yourself so that
you can take a look at it.
In fact, it's something
that you have seen before.
Now with all that list, all of
those ones are strong electrolytes.
So if it's not on that list as
a weak acid or base, that is
going to be a weak electrolyte.
So if it's not on the list,
that is a weak electrolyte.
And as a hint to remember, okay,
well, what's an acid, what's a base?
If it has an H in the front of
the formula, then it's an acid.
If there's an OH in the back,
then it's considered to be a base.
So remember that order when we're trying
to look at those different pieces,
so we can keep them all straight.
The last one is non electrolytes.
Now, non, or in this case,
whenever we have none of them,
are actually turning into ions.
So you'll have all these
dissolved solutes, which means
you have polar molecules.
Interacting through dipole dipole,
hydrogen bonding, you remember
the phrase like dissolves like.
Well, they dissolve, however,
they do not dissociate, so they
don't become cations and anions.
They stick together as covalent molecules.
They're a little too strong
to actually break apart.
So when that happens, what kind
of molecules are these like?
Well, for example, one of them
could be like a sugar molecule here.
If you have sugar, this
thing does not dissolve.
break apart into ions.
But you know that sugar dissolves, right?
You put in your tea, your
coffee, different fruit juices.
You know that it dissolves in all of them.
It's something that's in
a lot of our beverages.
So, how exactly does that look?
Well, if we were to write that, right,
if I had C6H12O6, well, it's a solid.
But once you throw it into water,
it's going to become aqueous, right?
So it's going to dissolve.
Now, being that it's still, notice
how it's still in its molecular form,
there's no plus or minus written.
This is referred to as a non
electrolyte because it still dissolves
being polar, but it's not, it's
not able to conduct electricity.
Right?
So it's not an actual electrolyte.
You can, you can ingest it, but it's not
going to give you those extra benefits
that are going to get absorbed and help
the different cells out in your body.
Let's practice what we just learned.
Indicate each of the following as strong,
weak, or non electrolytes in solution.
So when we are trying to look at
these different species, you will
have to identify them in your course.
So by doing that, what
exactly are you going to do?
So what we have to first try to figure
out is what type of compound is it?
So that way we can label if what
kind of electrolyte it's going to be.
So if I have this first one,
so it says it's sodium sulfate.
So, what exactly is it?
Well, we have to think, is
it ionic or is it covalent?
If you remember from your basic
definitions, ionic was a metal
and a non metal, or even more
specifically, a cation and anion.
So in this case, being that you see
sodium, right, which has a plus charge,
sulfate, which is a polyatomic, which
is two minus, you have your two charges,
meaning that it is an ionic compound.
And if you remember from
earlier, well, what is ionic?
Well, all ionic molecules are
considered to be a strong electrolyte.
So we'll label that as so.
Now for the next one, HF.
All right, so how exactly
can we do that one?
Well, if you remember, H has a plus
charge and fluorine has a minus charge.
However, Isn't this one covalent, right?
They're two non metals.
So is it going to be a non electrolyte?
But you got to remember, wait,
there's an hydrogen out front.
So what was that when we
had hydrogen out front?
This one is a weak acid.
So weak acids, because it's
not on your strong acid list.
The strong acids are HCl, HNO3,
sulfuric acid, chloride, chloric acid,
iodic acid, bromic acid, and so forth.
This is not one of them.
So what does that mean?
It's weak acid.
It's going to therefore be a weak
Electrolyte, so we'll put weak
here the next one ammonium nitrate.
So how can we label that?
Well, I remember that
nitrate is a polyatomic.
Well, what about ammonium?
Well, ammonium is also
one of our polyatomics.
It's, in fact, the only
positive polyatomic.
We see it's balanced.
Everything looks good.
So that means it's ionic.
Therefore, what does
that tell you about it?
That's going to be a strong electrolyte
as a result going to our next one.
Calcium hydroxide.
Okay, hydroxide.
So whenever we see that hydroxide,
we have to remember base.
So the question is, is
it a strong or weak?
So if you look at your list,
you're going to quickly see that
that's a strong base, meaning it's
going to be a strong electrolyte.
It's got the muscles behind it.
It can help break it apart.
Now, C3H6O, hmm, this
one's non ionic, right?
It's all non metals bound together.
So, and there's no hydrogen out
front and no OH in the back.
There are hydrogens and oxygens in it,
but it's not where they're supposed to be.
They must be covalent then, right?
If we ever see a carbon
molecule, it must be covalent.
It's probably an organic
molecule, meaning it's molecular.
So, if something is molecular,
how should we label that?
Well, That's going to be a
non electrolyte as a result.
Alright, so going through all those
little pieces, showing how they
could be soluble and dissolve.
Let's go on to one last example.
Okay, so looking at this one, which
picture best represents calcium nitrate?
When it comes to actually showing
these, you might have to look at
different diagrams to how to label
them and how are they represented.
Well, when we're doing that, we have to
realize how are they actually dissolving.
when you put them into solutions.
So these are your solubility
equations coming to play.
So whenever we have, let's say an ionic
compound, What we have to remember is
that the polyatomics always stay together.
They do not break apart
into their individual units.
Polyatomics are like a family.
They're always together.
So when we are going to draw
this, right, we have calcium is
going to be one of our species.
And then we are going to take that
subscript and it's going to become a
coefficient saying Ooh, this nitrate is
going to break down into Two individual
nitrates, and then we'll put our little
aqueous symbol here in front of all
these species because this is soluble.
So, looking at this, what we
should be seeing is something
along a similar criteria here.
It should be showing this nice
balanced formula where you have
this, these even, uh, this even
look, so we should see a one to two
ratio between calciums and nitrates.
So, where I'm kind of aiming
here is in the middle, we see
calciums and nitrates, so B and C.
So, which one is a 1 to 2 ratio?
B has 2 calciums, 4
nitrates, that's 1 to 2.
And here we have 2 calciums,
2 nitrates, that's a 1 to 1.
So, the most correct answer in
this case is going to be, now,
why weren't the other ones right?
Well, A, this one's like if you broke
everything, everything just broke
apart, all the ions, fell apart.
But you got to remember the nitrates
need to stick together for A.
In terms of D, it's kind of a similar
idea, but instead the nitrogens don't have
a charge, the oxygens don't have a charge.
That's really weird.
Um, even for a non electrolyte,
it wouldn't do that either.
It's just strange.
The A and D are strange.
The B would be your correct answer.
So this is the idea behind electrolytes.
So that way you can see how
many ions you have in solution.
So that way you're able to do
different calculations for, let's
say, colligative properties.
for molality and trying to understand
solubility and solubility trends.
All right, thank you so much
for listening, and I hope
you have a wonderful day.
If it's your first time here, please hit
that like and subscribe button, comment
below if you have any questions, and
I hope to see you all in the future.
Bye now!